<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Samson a type of Christ in a sermon preached at Mr. Pomfret's meeting-house in Gravel-lane near Hounds-ditch, London: at the morning-lecture, on July 22. 1691. from Judg. xiv.5. Then went Samson down, and his father and his mother, to Tunnath; and came to the vineyards of Timnath; and behold, a young lion roared against him. Wherein is shewed, I. In six particulars, how clearly Samson doth type forth Jesus Christ, ... II. With respect unto Samsons marriage, ... III. As Samson loved and married an uncircumcised woman, ... IV. As Samson did overcome the young lion which opposed him: so Jesus Christ doth overcome and destroy that roaring lion, the Devil, that opposeth him. Published at the request of the Congregation, for Publick Good. By D.C. an unworthy servant of Christ.</title>
            <author>Crosley, David, 1670-1744.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 102 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A81056</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C7247A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R232725</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99898047</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99898047</idno>
            <idno type="VID">171083</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A81056)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 171083)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2553:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Samson a type of Christ in a sermon preached at Mr. Pomfret's meeting-house in Gravel-lane near Hounds-ditch, London: at the morning-lecture, on July 22. 1691. from Judg. xiv.5. Then went Samson down, and his father and his mother, to Tunnath; and came to the vineyards of Timnath; and behold, a young lion roared against him. Wherein is shewed, I. In six particulars, how clearly Samson doth type forth Jesus Christ, ... II. With respect unto Samsons marriage, ... III. As Samson loved and married an uncircumcised woman, ... IV. As Samson did overcome the young lion which opposed him: so Jesus Christ doth overcome and destroy that roaring lion, the Devil, that opposeth him. Published at the request of the Congregation, for Publick Good. By D.C. an unworthy servant of Christ.</title>
                  <author>Crosley, David, 1670-1744.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 33, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for William Marshall at the Bible in [New]gate-street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1691.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With advertisements bound at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library, Oxford, England.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jesus Christ --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Judges XIV, 5 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christian literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Amanda Flynn</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Amanda Flynn</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:171083:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>SAMSON a Type of CHRIST: IN A SERMON PREACHED At Mr. Pomfret's Meeting-Houſe in Gravel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lane near Hounds-ditch, London: At the Morning-Lecture, on July 22. 1691. FROM <q>
                  <bibl>Judg. xiv. 5.</bibl> 
                  <hi>Then went Samſon down, and his Father and his Mother, to Timnath; and came to the Vineyards of Timnath; and Behold, a young Lion roared againſt him.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>WHEREIN IS SHEWED,
<list>
                  <item>I. In Six particulars, How clearly Samſon doth Type forth Jeſus Chriſt, viz. (1.) In his Conception and Birth. (2.) In his Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation and Manner of Life. (3.) In his Work and Office. (4.) In his Manner of Warfare. (5.) In his Marriage. (6.) And laſtly, In his Death. And,</item>
                  <item>II. With reſpect unto Samſons Marriage, (treated of in the Text) like as Samſon went down to Timnath a City of the Philiſtines to take a Wife: So Jeſus Chriſt came down from Heaven into this ſinfull World, to Redeem and Eſpouſe his Church to himſelf.</item>
                  <item>III. As Samſon loved and married an Uncircumciſed Woman, and one that belonged to the Houſe of his Enemies the Philiſtines: So Jeſus Chriſt Loved his Church when ſhe was Uncircumciſed in Heart, polluted in her Blood, and when reſiding in the Houſe of his Enemies, the Fallen Nature, he took her to himſelf.</item>
                  <item>IV. As Samſon did overcome the Young Lion which oppoſed him: So Jeſus Chriſt doth overcome and deſtroy that roaring Lion, the Devil, that oppoſeth him.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Publiſhed at the Requeſt of the Congregation, for Publick Good. By D. C. an unworthy Servant of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for William Marſhall at the Bible in Newgate-ſtreet, 1691.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:171083:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:171083:2"/>
            <head>To the READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT hath been, and is, to all the truly Godly, in this preſent Age, an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of great Trouble and Sorrow of Heart, to ſee the World ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly declining the Ways of God, and reducing it ſelf into ſuch an height of Conformity to the Will and Ways of the Devil, in this Generation; even ſuperabounding with all manner of Sin, and abominable Wickedneſs, and that in ſuch meaſures (to ſpeak no further) as former Ages have been abſolute ſtrangers to: And indeed, to ſee this in <hi>France, Spain</hi> and <hi>Italy,</hi> where it is to be feared they very much content themſelves with the very Name of Chriſtians, being with reſpect to Faith and Worſhip, even drowned in Idolatry and Superſtition, is a great pity, but not ſo much to be admired: But now to ſee this Notorious wickedneſs, and theſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard of ſins, So much in Credit and Practice in <hi>England,</hi> I ſay in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> a Nation ſo much admired and cryed up for Learning, Piety and Goſpel Light; truly this is not only much to be pitied, but alſo very much to be admired. And again, were but this Sin and Wickedneſs Thus in Credit and Practce among the Carnal and Irreligious ones, Who either profeſs nothing at all, or elſe content themſelves with meer formal Worſhip, in the mean while Denying the Life and Power of true Godlineſs; then it would not ſeem half ſo ſtrange neither: But now, that this Sin and Wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſs is as much, if not in ſome reſpects more, in Credit with, and in Practice amongſt, them, that of late years have born the Rod of Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution for Conſcience-ſake: Who have not only Diſſented from what they perceived in others to be too ſuperſtitious, but have ſeparated from the Ways of the Vulgar, and have joyned themſelves to the Lord, and to one another, in the ſtricteſt Sincerity and Zeal. Now I ſay, that this Sin and Wickellneſs ſhould ſo eaſily get amongſt, and be ſo readily entertained by theſe, yea by Theſe; O this is not only an occaſion of pity, but of Great Admiration and Aſtoniſhment to and amongſt all truly fearing God at this day. But if any ſay, What ſin is there amongſt ſuch? I anſwer, What ſin is there amongſt ſuch? Nay, thou mayſt rather ſay, What ſin is there not amongſt ſuch? Yet I do not mean ſins manifeſtly Groſs and notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly wicked; ſuch as is Drunkenneſs, Whoredom, Swearing, and appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently looſe Living: No, but I mean this Abominable Spirit of Pride, which certainly was ſcarce ever before at the height to which it is now ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived, both Externally and Internally, both in City and Countrey: For though it may be within, when it doth not manifeſtly appear outwardly; yet when it is ſo highly apparent without, there is black work within for certain.
<pb facs="tcp:171083:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> And alſo this exceſſive Covetouſneſs, yea and that with reſpect unto Goſpel-matters; of which (I fear I may too truely ſpeak it) the Miniſters are too highly (not to ſay moſt highly) Guilty: For Souls and Congregaetions are by many ſlighted and over-looked, where there is not that Honour, Advantage, Entertainment and Eſteem which this Ambitious Age calls for. And hence it cometh to paſs that the city is ready to ſurfeit with Superfluity, while the Countrey is almoſt ſtarved for want of Supply, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And 'tis well if too many, who have formerly condemned others, for that, for which they were indeed highly worthy of blame, do not now themſelves in this time of Liberty fall into the ſame ſnares with them: Beſides, there is a ſpirit of Envy and Evil-will, with the which the Minds of moſt Profeſſors at this Day are too highly influenced; which generally ariſes from a deſire, which now reigns in the Hearts of moſt to be Great and Lordly <hi>among,</hi> if not <hi>over</hi> their Fellow-brethren; the ſad Effects whereof many Congregations are too highly ſenſible at this day: But when <hi>Samſon</hi> comes down to <hi>Timnath,</hi> viz. When Chriſt comes down in more Light, Life and Power by the Goſpel, and amongſt his People, to the overcoming and flaying of this Lion, the Devil, the grand Author of all theſe Troubles Then will the Trumpet of the Goſpel ſound a Retreat, in order to the bringing back of backſliding Sion to her firſt Husband: Concerning which (Reader) thou haſt a ſhort Account given thee in this enſuing Diſcourſe; which, though it be unpoliſht, wanting thoſe learned Phraiſes and Terms of Art ſo much in uſe at this day, yet the Simpleneſs and Plainneſs thereof, may be Advantageous to ſuch as are of mean Capacities; and ſuch as are otherwiſe, are deſired to look over the ſame.</p>
            <p>And further know, that when it was preached, it was not at all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned for the Preſs: No, nothing leſs was in the Authors thoughts: But it being publickly requeſted before the Congregation went away, for that the People then preſent ſeemed to be very much Affected therewith; the Author was thereby engaged, together with ſome other reaſons of the like Import, to give way to the ſame, not much regarding what in a way of Deriſion may be charged upon him for the ſame.</p>
            <p>And now, Reader, that thou mayſt be Benefited, and the Lord alone Exalted, is both the Deſign of this, and Deſire of him, who remaineth a hearty Well-wiſher to all the whole <hi>Iſrael</hi> of God,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From my Chamber (for the preſent) in</hi> Lawrence-lane, <hi>near</hi> Cheap-ſide, London, <date>July <hi>28. 1691.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>David Croſſey.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:171083:3"/>
            <head>SAMSON <hi>a Type of</hi> CHRIST.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>JUDGES xiv. 5.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Then went Samſon down, and his Father, and his Mother, to Timnath, and came to the Vinyard of Timnath; and behold a young Lion roared againſt him.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>BELOVED, It is worth the ſerious Obſervation of all ſincere Chriſtians, to take notice, How God in days of old (eſpecially in the middle Age of the World) did lead his Church and People, by <hi>Types</hi> and <hi>Figures,</hi> to the Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Jeſus Chriſt, as by him appointed to be the only Saviour of all that believe in his Name throughout all Ages.</p>
            <p>SO that few Kings in, or Judges over <hi>Iſrael,</hi> for many hundred years together, but did in one thing or another, leſs or more, Typically repreſent Jeſus Chriſt, in his Perſon, Works, or Offices; as many both then, and alſo ſince, have to their comfort and benefit obſerved.</p>
            <p>AMONG whom <hi>Samſon,</hi> of whom our Text treateth, ſhineth in this reſpect, as a Star of the firſt magnitude; and doth in many things as clearly (if not more clearly) Type forth Chriſt, than any of them all; and that in many particulars. But I ſhall only mention ſix. 1. In his Birth. 2. In his Education. 3. In his Office and Government. 4. In his manner of Warfare. 5. In his Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage. 6. In his Death.</p>
            <p n="1">1ſt. IN his <hi>Birth,</hi> 1. In that it was foretold by <hi>Angels,</hi> Judg. 13.3. Anſwerable to the Birth of Chriſt, <hi>Luke</hi> 1.31. 2. In that it was in a time of <hi>Iſraels</hi> ſo great Bondage and Captivity, <hi>Judg.</hi> 13.1. So the Birth of Chriſt was in like manner when the Scepter was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:171083:4"/>from <hi>Judah,</hi> and all the World came up to be taxed by <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar,</hi> Luke 2.1, 2. 3. In that it was in a time of <hi>Iſraels</hi> ſo great Darkneſs, Blindneſs and wickedneſs, <hi>ch.</hi> 13.1. So the Birth of Chriſt, of whom it is ſaid, <hi>When he cometh, ſhall he find faith on earth?</hi> Luke 18.8. See alſo <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.10.</p>
            <p n="2">2dly. IN his Education, in that he was a <hi>Nazarite</hi> unto God from the Womb, devoted to the Lord from his Birth; and that not at his Parents Diſcretion, as <hi>Samuel,</hi> 1 Sam. 1.11. but of the Lord's own Choice, <hi>Judg.</hi> 13.5.</p>
            <p n="3">3dly. IN his Office and Government, he was, 1. To be a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverer to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> Judg. 13.5. 2. A Judge over <hi>Iſrael,</hi> Judg. 16.31. to ſave and defend them from the <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> who then ſo grievouſly oppreſſed and diſtreſſed them: accordingly as Chriſt was appointed and exalted of God to be a Prince and a Saviour in and over his Church, the Government whereof was and is upon <hi>his ſhoulders,</hi> Iſa. 9.6. Act. 5.31. And him it is that is in the <hi>midſt of her,</hi> and therefore ſhe ſhall not be <hi>moved,</hi> Pſal. 46.5. <hi>His tabernacle is in the midſt of her, and he will ſurely plead her cauſe.</hi> For <hi>whoſoever toucheth her, toucheth the apple of his eye,</hi> Zech. 2.8.</p>
            <p n="4">4thly. IN his manner of Warfare; and indeed this is worth the noting, and moſt obſerveable, in that when <hi>Samſon</hi> went to War with, or to Battel againſt his Adverſaries; as he often did, he never gathered together Armies of Men, nor called in Aſſiſtance from the People, as did others of the Judges and Kings of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> Nay, what Judge, Prince, King, or Monarch, did we ever read or hear of, that did not ſo, excepting him alone? But as for him (the Spirit of the Lord firſt coming upon him) he always went forth in his own Perſon againſt them, generally without any Weapons but what Providence brought to his hands: And yet we do not read that ever he went forth but he prevailed; he never Engaged, but he always Conquered, and came off Victorious, (except in the Matter of <hi>Dalilah,</hi> wherein he reſembles not <hi>Chriſt,</hi> but a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi>) in all things elſe he was ever ſucceſsful, putting whole Armies to flight, and overthrowing the power of the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> in ſuch a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner as gave way to <hi>Iſraels</hi> Reſtoration, both with reſpect to their Rights and Liberties. So that hence note, 1. That he finding <hi>Iſrael</hi> in ſo great Slavery and Bondage to the <hi>uncircumciſed Philiſtins,</hi> did firſt reſtore, ſet free, and redeem them, both with reſpect to their Liberties and Laws, in Perſons and Eſtates, making them again a free Nation. And then, 2. He did Judge, Defend and Preſerve
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:171083:4"/>them in the Liberties and Rights unto which he had reſtored them. And all this he did in his own Perſon, without having any Aſſiſtance or Counſel from his Brethren: No, all he got from them, was by them to be delivered Bound into the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> hands, had not the Lord reſcued him, <hi>Judg</hi> 15.11, 12, 13. which was but a fad requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal for the many and great Kindneſſes he had done them. But he takes all patiently from them, deſiring only of them, that they would not lay hands on him themſelves.</p>
            <p>And now who ſees not in all this, how clearly he types forth Jeſus Chriſt, the Heavenly and Spiritual Judge of the whole <hi>Iſrael</hi> of God, who taking up the (otherwiſe Loſt) Cauſe of fallen Man, in order to the bringing about of his Reſtoration and Redemption, firſt humbles himſelf, and becomes like one of his Brethren, yet without ſin, having both Natures in the unity of his Perſon; in which Perſon he goes forth againſt all the powers of Sin, Death and Hell, in the name and behalf of Man loſt in the Fall, and ſo proclaims open War againſt all Powers and Principalities oppoſing Man's Salvation. Againſt whom, upon every Engagement, he ſtill gets the victory, and comes off victorious in ſpite of all Oppoſitions, not ceaſing both to proceed and prevail till he hath compleated the work of his Peoples Redemption and Salvaaion. And all this he doth not only in his own Perſon, but alſo in his own Power, as the Son of God; for otherwiſe he acknowledgeth he could do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.30. (even as <hi>Samſon</hi> without his <hi>ſeven Locks</hi> was <hi>weak,</hi> and but as <hi>another man,</hi> Judg. 16.17.) But Chriſt, as the Son of God, <hi>trod the Wine-preſs alone,</hi> Iſa. 63.3. bore the Wrath and Curſe of God, endured the moſt bitter pangs of Death, and moſt intolerable torments of Hell, till the Father beheld, and ſaid he was ſatisfied, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.11. <hi>Mat.</hi> 17.5. and thereby he ſtopped the mouth of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring Juſtice, and took away by his Obedience, Paſſive and Active, all Power of Condemnation from the fiery Law, with reſpect to all New-Covenant Members; and ſo he aſcended up on high, and led Captivity Captive, depriving Death of its Sting, and the Grave of its Victory; thereby fulfilling every Condition in the New-Covenant, whereby it is made intirely free of it ſelf, and the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers thereby are made intirely free alſo in themſelves, as they come actually by Faith, through true Regeneration, to be inveſted therein. Here note, that Chriſt finding his People in the Gall of Bitterneſs, and Bond of Iniquity; dead in Sins and Treſpaſſes; ſhut up under Gates of Braſs, and Bars of Iron; charged with an infinite Debt, and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:171083:5"/>for that expos'd to eternal Miſery, if not immediately ſet free; and alſo inſulted over by the Devil, and trampled upon by all the powers of Hell: I ſay, Chriſt, when firſt appearing in the Fleſh, finding his Inheritance given him by the Father, <hi>Joh.</hi> 7.6. thus given over to Strangers, doth firſt releaſe and ſet them all at liberty, by paying all their Debt for them, and ſuing forth of the Court of Heaven a free and full Diſcharge in their behalf; ſubduing withall in due time all their Enemies both within and without, doth in the ſecond place defend and preſerve them in this liberty and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly freedom to which he hath reſtored them: And all this by vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of his own Power and Merit, without any aſſiſtance from them either in whole or in part. Nay, He, as <hi>Samſon,</hi> was delivered up by his Brethren, the Men of his own Nation, into the hands of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Infidels, to be Crucified and put to death, a ſad requital to him for his kindneſs. Nay, further I may ſpeak it, and you hear it with ſorrow and ſhame, Where is the Chriſtian who in a ſpiritual ſenſe doth not again and again give Chriſt over, ſo far as lyeth in his power, to be Crucified over and over, by giving way to the Enemy to take poſſeſſion of his Heart? But happy they that lay not hands upon him themſelves, on purpoſe and in deſpite, for that is the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pardonable Sin. But I haſte.</p>
            <p n="5">5thly. <hi>SAMSON</hi> typifies Chriſt in his <hi>Marriage.</hi> This is the Point upon which our Text treateth, we will therefore paſs it by till we come to the words.</p>
            <p n="6">6thly. HE typifies Chriſt in his <hi>Death:</hi> For it is ſaid of him, That he gave his Enemies a greater ſtroke, and did more execution among them at the day of his death, than he had done in all his life-time, <hi>Judg.</hi> 16.30. Which is more eſpecially true in Chriſt Jeſus; for he gave the Powers of Hell a greater ſtroke at the day and hour of his Death, than he had done in all his Life-time by his Word and Miracles; for then it was that <hi>by death he overcame him that had the power of death, that is, the Devil,</hi> Heb. 2.14. Then it was that he took away the Hand-writing of Ordinances that was againſt us, which was contrary to us, nailing it to his Croſs, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.14 and having ſpoiled Principalities and Powers, he made a Show of them, openly triumphing over them in it. Then it was, that through the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Spirit he offered up himſelf to God without ſpot; whereby he became the Mediator of the New Teſtament, to the end, that by the means of Death, for the Redemption of the Tranſgreſſions that were under the Firſt Covenant, they which are called might receive
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:171083:5"/>the promiſe of an Eternal Inheritance, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.15. Then it was that he was once offered to bear the ſins of many, and unto them that look for him, he will appear the ſecond time without ſin unto Salvation: Bleſſed are all they that wait for him in ſincerity.</p>
            <p>BUT I come to the matter in hand.</p>
            <p>AND in the firſt place I would note by the way four things, from the four firſt Verſes of this Chapter, antecedent to our Text.</p>
            <p n="1">1ſt. <hi>SAMSON</hi>'s falling in Love with a Woman in <hi>Timnath,</hi> a Daughter of the Philiſtines, (<hi>Ver.</hi> 1.) and from hence I obſerve, That as <hi>Samſon</hi> loved this Philiſtine Woman, though dwelling in the Houſe of his Enemies, and ſo by nature one of them; ſo alſo Jeſus Chriſt loved his Church when in the Houſe of his Enemies, <hi>viz.</hi> the fallen Eſtate; and not only ſo, but whilſt ſhe was an Enemy he laid down his Life for her, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.8.</p>
            <p n="2">2dly. THE oppoſitions he met with from his Father and his Mother in the purſuit of his Deſires in taking her to be his Wife, (<hi>ver.</hi> 3.) and hence I obſerve, That Perſons out of a ſincere Zeal, may ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times oppoſe God in his moſt Wiſe and oft times various Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations.</p>
            <p n="3">3dly. THE Reaſons moving them ſo to do, (<hi>ver.</hi> 3.) which was, becauſe ſhe was a Stranger of another Nation, and uncircumciſed; and the Iſraelites were forbidden to Marry with ſuch by the Law, <hi>Deut.</hi> 7.3. And from thence I obſerve, That God can turn all things, yea even ſin it ſelf, ſo, as that it ſhall conduce abundantly to his Glory and his Peoples good, benefit and advantage.</p>
            <p n="4">4thly. I would note <hi>Samſon</hi>'s Anſwer to his Father and Mother when by them oppoſed for loving of this Daughter of the Philiſtines, <hi>Get her for me, for ſhe pleaſeth me well.</hi> And from hence I obſerve, 1. That as no Oppoſitions nor Perſwaſions could remove <hi>Samſon</hi>'s Affections from this Philiſtine Woman, ſo nothing, no not ſin it ſelf, could nor can ever be able to ſeparate or remove the Love of Chriſt from his Church, <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.3. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.38, 39. But contrariwiſe, the Love of Chriſt will move him to ſeperate and remove all ſin, with what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever elſe offends him, from her, in his own time. 2. As the want of Circumciſion, and ſeveral other things required by the Law, could not prevent <hi>Samſon</hi>'s loving and marrying of this Philiſtine Woman, ſo want of inherent Qualifications, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> cannot hinder Chriſt's loving and eſpouſing of his Church to himſelf, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.6, 7, 8. But contrariwiſe, his Love to her hath, doth, and will move him to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:171083:6"/>waſh and cleanſe her, fit and qualifie her, renew, enrich, and adorn her ſo, as may render her moſt well-pleaſing in his Eyes, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.9, 10, 11, 12, &amp; 13.</p>
            <p>AND this brings me to our Text, in which I would note four things alſo.</p>
            <p n="1">1ſt. <hi>SAMSON</hi>'s Journey down to <hi>Timnath,</hi> a City of the Philiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and from hence take this Propoſition; That as <hi>Samſon</hi> went down to <hi>Timnath,</hi> a City of the Philiſtines, to take a Wife from thence; ſo Jeſus Chriſt came down from Heaven into this ſinful be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wildered World to purchaſe Marriage, and Betroth unto himſelf his beloved Church and Spouſe, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2.19. <hi>Jer.</hi> 3.14.</p>
            <p n="2">2dly. HIS occaſion thither, which was to Marry the Woman whom Love (notwithſtanding her nonconformity to the Laws and Cuſtoms of <hi>Iſrael</hi>) had made ſo well-pleaſing unto him. And from hence take a ſecond Propoſition, That as Love was the only impulſive or moving cauſe which brought <hi>Samſon</hi> down to <hi>Timnath</hi> to Marry this Woman, who otherwiſe could not have been accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to, no more than ſhe was in an Eye of reaſon fit, for him: ſo likewiſe meer Love was the impulſive cauſe which alone moved Jeſus Chriſt to come down upon the Earth to Marry his Church unto himſelf, whom had ſhe not been ſo loved by him, could never have otherwiſe been acceptable to him, being in her fallen Eſtate, in an eye of reaſon upon all accounts ſo unfit for him.</p>
            <p n="3">3dly. HIS Company which went down with him, which was his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and his Mother, he would do nothing in the caſe without their Company and Conſent, which affords us this third Propoſition, That as <hi>Samſon,</hi> notwithſtanding the ardency of his Love, would do nothing without the knowledge, advice, company and conſent of his Father and Mother; ſo Jeſus Chriſt in all his Proceedings in and towards his Church, did not only in all things conform to the Will of his Father, but alſo had the Father ſtill preſent with him to bear him company, <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.39. And ſo much was he delighted therein, that when, through exceſſive ſorrow and trouble, he had but the leaſt apprehenſion of his Fathers abſence, how vehemently did he cry out, <hi>Ely, Ely, Lama ſabachthani,</hi> i. e. <hi>My God, my God, why haſt thou for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken me,</hi> Mat. 27.46. Oh happy that Man or Woman among us this day, that is thus tender on, and deſirous of the Heart-inriching Soul-raviſhing Love, Company and Preſence of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:171083:6"/>
            <p>But again, 4thly. LET us note the terrible oppoſition that <hi>Sam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> met with in his Journey, even when he came nigh to the place; ſo the Text, coming to the Vineyards of <hi>Timnath, Behold, a young Lion roared againſt him:</hi> Young, noting vigour and nimbleneſs; a young Lion, noting ſtrength, cruelty and fierceneſs, a frightful Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary indeed, eſpecially conſidering how unprepared <hi>Samſon</hi> was to an eye of reaſon for ſuch an Aſſault; which affords us this fourth and laſt Propoſition, <hi>viz.</hi> That as <hi>Samſon</hi> in going about to Marry and Eſpouſe this Woman of <hi>Timnath,</hi> this Daughter of the Phili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtines to himſelf, met with many oppoſitions, but more eſpecially this young Lion; ſo Jeſus Chriſt in endeavouring the Redemption and Eſpouſal of his Church unto himſelf, hath and doth meet with many oppoſitions, but eſpecially that roaring Lion the Devil, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.8. For, 1. when he was in the Fleſh in order to the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhment of Mans Redemption, how often did this Lion, this Devil, ſet upon him, and not contenting himſelf with daily trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling, vexing and perſecuting of him by his wicked Inſtruments the Jews, he firſt drives him into the Wilderneſs to tempt him there, where he deals with him as it were Hand to Fiſt, but ſtill doth no good. Again, 2. He ſtirs up his Diſciples to moleſt and grieve him, firſt <hi>Peter</hi> by his fleſhly advice; hence Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Get thee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind me Satan, &amp;c.</hi> Mat. 16.23. Then, ſecondly, <hi>Judas</hi> to betray him; for ſaith the Text, <hi>Satan entered into him again.</hi> Thirdly, <hi>Peter</hi> to deny him, and that with Oaths, ſaying, <hi>I know not the Man.</hi> Oh horrible! And after all this, he again comes himſelf (as it were) accompanied with all the Powers of Hell to aſſiſt him, and taking him at the greateſt diſadvantage, even when under the heavy burden of his Fathers Wrath, according to <hi>Pſal.</hi> 69.26. as deſigning, if poſſible, at once to ſtrike him down to Hell for ever. But bleſſed be God, it was not poſſible, <hi>&amp;c. Joh.</hi> 14.30. <hi>The prince of this world cometh and hath nothing in me.</hi> See then the Devils Malice, though he had nothing in Chriſt, yet would he not ceaſe to afflict Chriſt whilſt in his reach; and he carries the ſame mind towards Chriſtians alſo, <hi>Luke</hi> 22.31, 32. <hi>Simon, Simon, Satan hath deſired to have you, that he may ſift you as Wheat, &amp;c.</hi> Again, ſecondly, when he cometh in the Spirit, in and by the Goſpel, actually to call and unite his People to himſelf, the Devil ſtill ceaſeth not to interrupt him in his Proceedings, if by any means he can, although in this reſpect he doth not directly ſo much fight againſt Chriſt as Chriſtians; for he knows he can do no good with him, he long ſince overcame him up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:171083:7"/>
               <hi>Mount Calvary,</hi> Heb. 2.14. By death he overcame him that hath the power of Death, even the Devil. And now ſeeing he can do no good on Chriſt the Husband, he deſires to have poor Believers the Church, that he may try and ſift them as Wheat: And truly, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved, the Devil hath put many a poor Chriſtian hard to it, he hath made many a one cry out, <hi>Oh what ſhall I do?</hi> And I doubt not but many of you in this Congregation have met with him to your ſorrow; and ſo by woful experience know theſe things I now ſpeak to be true.</p>
            <p>BUT to all you that are labouring in this bitter warfare and hour of tryal, this day of <hi>Jacob</hi>'s trouble, let me ſay thus much to you, Have a care of truſting to the Arm of Fleſh, and of putting confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in Man; Have a care of ſelling your ſelves for nought, by putting confidence in that which cannot ſave; but conſider our great <hi>Samſon</hi> is ſpiritually come down in and by the Goſpel, and he is among us and preſent with us, and if he do but as much as ſhew his Head or make bare his Arm in any of our Hearts and Souls, then the Devil is gone, he is fled, and though we ſeek him at ſuch a time we cannot find him; and why? well, becauſe Chriſt is come down to dwell with us. Oh, Sirs, could we but live more by Faith with and in Chriſt, we ſhould be leſs troubled with the Devils Company. But I haſte.</p>
            <p>BELOVED, time will not permit me to ſpeak to all theſe Four Propoſitions thus raiſed from the words, I ſhall therefore make choice of the Fourth and laſt of them, for the ſubject of my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining Diſcourſe at this time, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THAT as <hi>Samſon</hi> in going about to Marry and Eſpouſe this Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of <hi>Timnath,</hi> this Daughter of the Philiſtines to himſelf, did meet with many Oppoſitions, chiefly this young Lion; ſo Jeſus Chriſt endeavouring the Redemption and Eſpouſal of his Church to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, hath and doth meet with many Oppoſitions and Oppoſers, but eſpecially that roaring Lion the Devil.</p>
            <p>IN the handling of which Point, I ſhall obſerve this Method:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> TO ſhew the State and Condition of Chriſt's Church in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, and every Member thereof in particular, before called by, and United or Married unto Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> I ſhall conſider whether the Church firſt ſeeketh unto Chriſt, or Chriſt unto the Church, in order unto the effecting of this Bleſſed Union or Marriage.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:171083:7"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> MENTION ſome of the greateſt Lets, Hindrances and Impediments, which do moſt interrupt this Bleſſed Union and Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment betwixt Chriſt and his Church.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> I ſhall give you ſome Cautions in order to a timely pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention of the dangers occaſioned thereby.</p>
            <p>And, <hi>Laſtly,</hi> MAKE ſome ſhort Application.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> I ſhall ſhew the State and Condition of Chriſt's Church in general, and of every Member thereof in particular, before called by, and United or Married unto Jeſus Chriſt: but I muſt be brief in the whole.</p>
            <p>And, <hi>Firſt,</hi> THE State of Chriſt's Church in general, and of every Member thereof in particular before called, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is a State of Deadneſs: This is plain from <hi>Paul</hi>'s words to the Church at <hi>Epheſus, Fph.</hi> 2.1. <hi>But you hath he quickened, who were dead in ſins and treſpaſſes.</hi> See alſo <hi>verſ.</hi> 4, &amp; 5. Now this deadneſs is two-fold: 1. A deadneſs to God and all Goodneſs: And this deadneſs is, 1. Abſolute: And, 2. Univerſal. 1. Abſolute, not a deadneſs in part, as ſome do vain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly imagine, as if Man was partly dead, and partly alive to God by Nature: No, for Man is wholly dead, ſo as that there is no Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Life to Heavenly things remaining in him. 2dly, It is an Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal deadneſs, or a deadneſs throughout: <hi>Death,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.12. <hi>paſt upon all men, for that all have ſinned:</hi> And as it paſſed upon all, ſo it obtained a Compleat Dominion over all; ſo that take an unconverted Man, that is altogether natural, and ſuch a Man is, with reſpect unto God, a dead Man; his Heart, his Will, his Mind, his Affections, together with all other Faculties of the Soul, are altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther dead, and lifeleſs. And, ſecondly, it is a deadneſs <hi>in</hi> ſin, not <hi>to</hi> ſin, for ſo is the truly godly, according to their meaſures, but a deadneſs <hi>in</hi> ſin: Hence note, a natural Man thus dead in ſin, is Firſt not ſenſible of ſin; ſecondly, he is not troubled for ſin; thirdly, he is not burdened with ſin; fourthly, he hath no true deſire to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered from ſin: true, he may have ſome Convictions, and perhaps ſometimes ſharp ones too, but it is either not for ſin as ſin, or elſe but for ſome particular Acts of ſin more notorious than ordinary; in the mean while, not ſeeing that his whole Nature is polluted, and that the beſt of his Actions, whilſt out of Chriſt, is but as filthy Rags, which inſtead of meriting any good thing for him, doth rather, like the Blood of <hi>Abel,</hi> cry to Heaven for vengeance upon him; for without Chriſt we can do nothing, <hi>John</hi> 15.5. that
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:171083:8"/>is, nothing well-pleaſing to him, <hi>for whatſoever is not of faith is ſin.</hi> O that the World could once be brought to ſee this! then Men would have done talking of Free-will, and of a power in Man, whilſt in Nature, to do that which is good; then would they be brought off truſting in, depending upon, or boaſting of their own Righteouſneſs; then ſhould we all fall down as one Man before the Lord, crying out as with one Voice, <hi>Oh wretched men that we are, who ſhall deliver us from this body of ſin?</hi> Rom. 7. 24. Then ſhould we know what Chriſt meaneth in that notable place, <hi>John</hi> 5. 24, 25.</p>
            <p>But, <hi>Secondly,</hi> THE State of Chriſt's Church in general, and of every Member thereof in particular, before called by him, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is a State of Hardneſs and deſperate Wickedneſs; but ſtill I mean as to the things of God: for, alas! if the Devil tempt, if the World allure, if the Fleſh luſt after its own things, if any Profit, Pleaſure, Honour, Preferment, or Advantage be offered to us, Oh how ſoon then have we an Eye to ſee, an Ear to hear, and an open Heart to receive theſe things, though tending never ſo much to our Souls ruine and deſtruction! but on the other hand, God may call and call again, he may ſtand at the Door and knock day after day, he may cry aloud in our Ears by his Word, Works and Providences, he may threaten Death, Damnation and Deſtruction by the Law; and again ſweetly tender Grace, Mercy, Forgiveneſs of Sins and Salvation, by the Goſpel, time after time, and in Sermon after Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, and yet for all this, Man, whilſt in Nature, hath neither Eye to ſee, Ear to hear, nor Heart to receive: Oh ſad Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition!</p>
            <p>But again, <hi>Thirdly,</hi> THE State of Chriſt's Church in general, and of every Member thereof in particular, before called by Chriſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is a State of Blindneſs and Inſenſibility; for though Man in this Eſtate lie in the Gall of Bitterneſs and Bond of Iniquity, chained up in the Devils Priſon, where Satan himſelf is Gaoler, though he be in a State which if lived and dyed in, will certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly uſher him into the Pit of Hell; and though he be poſting with the greateſt Expedition towards everlaſting Damnation, ſleeping and ſnoring in a Condition near equivalent to the Damned in Hell, and though he hear all this from the Scriptures and God's Miniſters, yet ſtill he remains blind and inſenſible, till God move upon the Heart. See <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.18.</p>
            <p>But, <hi>Fourthly,</hi> FOR I haſte, The State of the Church of Chriſt, and every Member thereof, whilſt in Nature and uncalled, is a ſtate
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:171083:8"/>of Alienation from God: Alas! whilſt thus, they have no true knowledge of him, nor fellowſhip with him, they ſee him not, nor enjoy him, though in him they live, move and have their Being; they riſe up in the Morning, and ly down again at Night, Day after Day, Month after Month, and yet have not God in a godly way as much as once in all their thoughts; they rarely do as much as once ſeriouſly conſider whether they be going, to Life or Death, to Heaven or Hell, to God or the Devil.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> and laſtly, THE State of Chriſt's Church in general, and every Member thereof in particular, before effectually called by Chriſt to himſelf, is a State of Deceiveableneſs: This <hi>Paul</hi> confeſſeth to <hi>Titus, Titus</hi> 3.3. For, alas! generally, nay, I think I may ſay always, they that are moſt without God have the leaſt ſenſe of the want of God; they that are moſt with the Devil, are in the leaſt fear of the Devil, and they that are really the greateſt ſinners, are the leaſt troubled for their ſins; for either they are wholly Carnal in their Lives as well as Hearts, and ſo minding no Religon at all, or elſe they fall a doing and working for Life, build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon their Prayers, Duties, Works and Obedience, thinking theſe ſhall ſtand them in ſome ſtead; concluding, that if they can but live Civilly, deal Juſtly, do their Duties orderly, and keep all God's Commandments to the utmoſt of their Power, according to the Law: Well then, undoubtedly all ſhall be well with them, both in Death and Judgment, and conſequently to Eternity, though they know nothing, no nothing of Chriſt, the Goſpel, Faith, nor Self-denyal; not minding that the Scripture ſaith, That there is <hi>no name given under heaven whereby we can be ſaved,</hi> but the <hi>name of Jeſus;</hi> and that <hi>whoſoever believes not in him ſhall be damned,</hi> for without Faith it is impoſſible to pleaſe him; but <hi>Do</hi> and <hi>Live</hi> is the only Religon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with the fallen Nature, it is wholly a ſtranger to all Goſpel Myſteries, and ſo I fear are too many called Goſpel Miniſters, elſe why is Free-will and Mans works and Righteouſneſs cry'd up at ſuch a height at this day, to the great diſhonour of Chriſt and the Goſpel in ſo many places and perſons? and why is there ſuch Heart-burnings againſt ſuch as preach the Pure Goſpel of Chriſt, whereby Man and his Righteouſneſs is laid in the Duſt, and Chriſt and his Righteouſneſs exalted, according to the Scriptures? But to conclude this Point, <hi>Paul</hi> moſt plainly tells us what all Men are by Nature: For indeed there is no difference. In the ſecond of the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> 11, 12. 1ſt. Gentiles in the Fleſh. 2ly. Uncircumciſed
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:171083:9"/>in Heart. 3ly. Without Chriſt. 4ly. Aliens to the Commonwealth of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> 5ly. Strangers to the Covenant of Grace. 6ly. Void of Hope. 7ly. Without God in the World: a dreadful Condition in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed; and this brings me to the <hi>Second</hi> Particular.</p>
            <p>To conſider, Whether the Church firſt ſeeketh unto Chriſt; or on the contrary, Chriſt firſt ſeeketh unto the Church, in order to the effecting of this bleſſed Union or Marriage betwixt them. And the Solution is plain, Firſt, as intimated by the Text; and 2ly. As confirmed by all the Scriptures relating thereunto: 1ſt. As intimated by the Text, thus, <hi>viz.</hi> As <hi>Samſon</hi> firſt ſought unto, and endeavoured after this <hi>Philiſtine</hi> Woman, in order to the concluding of this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract betwixt them, and not ſhe unto him: So in like manner Jeſus Chriſt firſt and primarily ſeeketh unto his Church, in order to the bringing about of this happy Union, and not ſhe unto him. This alſo is plain from many Scriptures, as from the 16th. of <hi>Eezekiel,</hi> from the 3d. Verſe to the 14th. Where 1ſt. The Church lay in the open Field <hi>polluted in her blood.</hi> 2ly. There was <hi>no eye to pitty her.</hi> And yet, 3ly. When ſhe was in this condition, Jeſus Chriſt in mercy came and <hi>paſſed by.</hi> And 4ly. Her <hi>time,</hi> notwithſtanding her miſery and ſhame, was to him <hi>a time of love.</hi> And 5ly. He did all this whilſt ſhe in her ſelf was dead, as to any Affection towards him; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſaith he, <hi>ver.</hi> 6. <hi>And when I paſſed by thee, and ſaw thee polluted in thy own blood, I ſaid unto thee, Live; yea, when thou waſt in thy blood, I ſaid unto thee, Live.</hi> See alſo the 2d. of <hi>Hoſea,</hi> where when the Church was backſliden from, and which is worſe, (though al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways the iſſue of a backſliding Spirit,) hardned againſt him: Then he came in Mercy (though ſhe perhaps at the firſt did not ſo look upon it) and hedged up her way with Thorns, to the end that though ſhe purſued after her Lovers, yet that ſhe might not overtake them, <hi>ver.</hi> 6, 7. 2dly. He takes away all her Fulneſs, Joy, and Mirth, all her Delight in her own ways, and removes from her all her plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant things, <hi>ver.</hi> 9, 10, 11, 12. 3dly. He viſits upon her all the days of her former Wickedneſs and Idolatry, <hi>ver.</hi> 13. And, 4thly. After all this, he, as it were, turns Suiter to her: <hi>For</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>I will allure her, and bring her into the wilderneſs, and there will I ſpeak com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortably unto her,</hi> ver. 14. Alas, poor dejected, doubting Souls! whilſt God is a bringing of them into the Wilderneſs, or into a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wildered ſtate, as to their own Apprehenſions, are even frightned with fears and terrors, leſt he ſhould deſtroy them there, and give them over to periſh for ever, little conſidering that it is God's way
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:171083:9"/>to keep his beſt Wine till the latter end of the Feaſt; and in the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs to ſpeak moſt comfortably to them, giving them in the Valley of <hi>Achor,</hi> or Trouble, a Door of Hope; and that there the Knot of Union is to be tied, which is never to be looſed more; and that then they muſt call him no more <hi>Baali,</hi> viz. <hi>My Lord,;</hi> but that they muſt henceforth call him <hi>Iſhi,</hi> that is to ſay, <hi>My Husband,</hi> v. 16. A bleſſed Concluſion! And let me tell you, There is none of you here this day that are Suiters to God, but God hath had firſt a great ſuiting of you to bring you to that. Oh! admirable Love and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcention! that ever the Great God of Heaven, and Lord of Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, ſhould become Suiters to ſuch Hell-hounds as the beſt of us are by Nature. Again, Obſerve that Text in <hi>Jer.</hi> 3.12, &amp; 22. where the Lord moſt earneſtly and compaſſionately ſuiteth, exhorteth and inviteth his Church, with all poſſible perſuaſions, to return from her backſlidings; for, ſaith he, <hi>I am married unto you,</hi> ver. 14. <hi>only ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge your iniquities, and that you have tranſgreſſed againſt me:</hi> And then, <hi>Return, Oh hackſliding Children, and I will heal your backſlidings.</hi> And indeed here the Lord not only ſuited, but prevailed: For mark the Anſwer they returned him, <hi>ver.</hi> 22, 23. <hi>Behold we come unto thee, for thou art the Lord our God, in vain is ſalvation looked for from the hills, and from the multitude of mountains, for in the Lord our God is the ſalvation of Iſrael.</hi> The God of Heaven grant that we may return him the like Anſwer with Heart and Mouth, this day, and all other times wherein he by the Goſpel is inviting us to come unto him. See alſo the words of <hi>David,</hi> Pſal. 27.8. <hi>When thou, O Lord, ſaidſt, Seek ye my face; my heart ſaid unto thee, Thy face, Lord, will I ſeek.</hi> Oh dear Friends! hath not God a long time been a ſuiting of you by the Goſpel to come unto him? and hath he not often called aloud of you, ſaying, <hi>Seek ye my face?</hi> I know you cannot deny this. Well, but let me ask, Was you ever brought to cry out with <hi>David, Thy face, O Lord, will I ſeek?</hi> True, it may be you have ſaid thus with your Mouths; but pray note, Did your Hearts ever ſay ſo? Saith holy <hi>David, My heart ſaid, Thy face, O Lord, will I ſeek.</hi> Pray con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider it. But to conclude this Point alſo, Mind what <hi>John</hi> ſaith in his <hi>Firſt Epiſtle,</hi> 4.10, &amp; 19. <hi>Herein is love,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>not that we loved God, but that he loved us;</hi> And we love him, becauſe he lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved us firſt. Alas, Beloved! had not God loved and ſought after <hi>us,</hi> till we had loved and ſought after <hi>him,</hi> then had we never ſo much as once lifted up our Eyes towards him, till with the Rich Man we had been in Hell; which would have been too late either to have
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:171083:10"/>ſought after him, or looked up unto him. I might mention many more Scriptures to the like Effect, but time will not permit. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, theſe are ſufficient already laid down, the ſequel whereof amounts to this, That as <hi>Samſon</hi> firſt ſought unto this Woman of <hi>Timnath,</hi> this Daughter of the Philiſtines, notwithſtanding her Non-conformity to the Religion and Laws of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and not ſhe unto him: So Jeſus Chriſt ſeeketh unto his Church in true Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly and Divine Love, and not ſhe unto him, notwithſtanding, not only her Nonconformity to, but alſo her Enmity againſt the Religion and Laws of his Kingdom, as ſhe lyeth in Nature, and when he thus firſt applyeth himſelf unto her.</p>
            <p>AND from hence I inferr,</p>
            <p>FIRST, That Chriſt in ſeeking after, and calling of his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to himſelf, hath no reſpect to Antecedent Qualifications in them, for he knows better than we, the impoſſibility that a bitter Fountain ſhould yield ſweet Water, or a bad Tree bring forth good Fruit: Therefore ſaith he to the Phariſees, <hi>Oh generation of Vipers, how can ye being evil, do that,</hi> or as the word is, <hi>ſpeak that which is good, for out of the abundance of the Heart the Mouth ſpeaketh,</hi> Mat 12.34. But a Blind Man will not believe this, becauſe he is Blind, and cannot ſee nor underſtand the Truth: But ſaith <hi>Calvin,</hi> 
               <q rend="margQuotes">What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever a Man thinketh, purpoſeth or doth, before he be recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled to God by Faith in Chriſt, is accurſed; and not only of no value to righteonſneſs, but of certain deſerving to Damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: <hi>Inſtitut.</hi> pag. 370.</q> And ſaith <hi>Luther,</hi> 
               <q rend="margQuotes">Whoſoever goeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to pleaſe God with works done before Faith, goeth about to pleaſe God with Sin, which (ſaith he) is nothing elſe, but to heap Sin upon Sin, mock God, and to provoke him to Wrath: O that men would once conſider theſe things!</q>
            </p>
            <p>SECONDLY, From hence I inferr, That though the Church of Chriſt in general, and every Member thereof in particular, be brought by Sin through the Fall into a loſt Eſtate, which, as was before obſerved, is a State of Deadneſs, Hardneſs, Blindneſs and Alienation from God; yet there is a time wherein he will gather and call them all home to himſelf. There was a time in which <hi>Sam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> went down to <hi>Timnath,</hi> to take this Daughter of the Phili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtines to Wife: And accordingly there is a Time wherein God will gather his Elect from the four Winds of the Heavens: There is a Time for every one of Gods Jewels to be gathered into his Treaſure, and for every one of his Sheep to be brought into his
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:171083:10"/>Fold; tho' God's People be born in Sin, He will not have them to dye ſo: for there is a time, wherein <hi>I ſaith the Lord will call her Beloved that was not Beloved.</hi> And this hath the Father appointed, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.10. <hi>That in the diſpenſation of the fulneſs of times he might ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther together in one all things in Chriſt, both which are in Heaven, and which are on Earth, even in him.</hi> And, beloved, this time ſhall aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuredly come upon every Soul belonging to God: the Lord ſtir up our Hearts to look for it, for <hi>except we be converted and born again, we can never enter into the Kingdom of God.</hi> An uncalled State is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a dreadful State, for while a Man is ſo, he knows not whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he belong to God or no: But certainly ſuch a one may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that for the preſent he belongs unto the Devil, the Lord awaken all ſuch.</p>
            <p>THIRDLY, From hence I would inferr, That God muſt condeſcend and come down to us, (which indeed he hath done both in Fleſh and Spirit) before we can aſcend to him. So <hi>Samſon</hi> went down to <hi>Timnath.</hi> A Man whilſt in Nature, and ſo conſequently dead in Sin, is no more able truly and ſincerely to aſcend up to God, either in Affection, Faith or Practice, than a Stone to lift up it ſelf into the Air, or a Bird to ſtye which hath no wings: What could the <hi>dry Bones</hi> do, which the Lord ſaith was the Houſe of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> till the Spirit of the Lord came upon them? <hi>Ezek.</hi> 37. What cauſe then hath every Soul amongſt us to be humble be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord, and to be abaſed in our own Eyes, and to cry out with <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 115. 1. <hi>Not unto us, O Lord, not unto us, but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thy Name be praiſe!</hi> and with <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.7. <hi>What have we that we have not received?</hi> And with <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> Chapter 26. 12. <hi>Thou, O Lord haſt wrought all our works in us!</hi> But many Profeſſors at this day ſuppoſe a poſſibility of ſetting up Chriſt too high, and of laying Man down too low in himſelf: But how this cometh to paſs I could never yet underſtand: ſure I am there is a great deal of both Poſſibility and Danger of ſetting up Man and his Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs too high, and thereby diſeſteeming of Chriſt, and his precious Death and Merits: never was there leſs reaſon to cry up Mans Works and Obedience, (I mean ſo as to boaſt thereof, or depend thereupon) than at this day, in which they are (I may ſpeak it with ſorrow) ſo little practiſed. But were but the Free Grace of God, Chriſt Jeſus, and Faith in him duly exalted, and freely preached in Life and Power, it would I think be the only way, truly and without Hypocriſie, to reform Mens Lives, and to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:171083:11"/>work their Hearts into a godly ſorrow, which would iſſue in it true and evangelical Repentance never to be repented of; but there being ſo much Legality among Profeſſers at this day, hath undoubted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly been a great occaſion of ſo much lukewarmneſs in the World in Matters of Religion.</p>
            <p>BUT I come to the Third Particular; <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>TO mention ſome of the greateſt Lets, Hindrances and Impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which do moſt interrupt this bleſſed Union and Agreement betwixt Chriſt and his Church; which indeed are many, but time will but permit me to mention ſome few.</p>
            <p>AND the firſt main Let or Hinderance, is the want of a thorough ſight, and a true ſenſe of the Miſerableneſs of the condition in which we are by Nature; and accordingly an enjoyment of reſt and ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, though both falſe and Soul-deſtructive in that condition. And thus much even Nature it ſelf teacheth, That no Man will ſeek unto a Phyſician for a cure, unleſs he be firſt ſenſible that he is trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with ſuch a Diſtemper as doth neceſſarily call for, and require ſuch a Cure: And who knows not, that even the beſt of us are a great deal more ready and forward to encline to, and ſeek after the Benefit and Cure of the Body, than the Benefit and Cure of the Soul; inſomuch that a Man of whom I have heard, who deſerting and forſaking the Work of the Miniſtry, in which he had ſpent much labour and travel, to take up the Practice of Phyſick; and being asked the reaſon why? He returned this Anſwer, <hi>Becauſe</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>I ſaw People were a great deal more careful of their Bodies than of their Souls, and much more free to lay out their Money and Pains for the one than the other.</hi> And Chriſt himſelf tells us, <hi>That the whole need not a Phyſician, but they that are ſick.</hi> The reaſon therefore why Chriſt, our great Phyſician of Souls, is ſo much ſlighted, is becauſe ſo few are ſenſible of their Souls Maladies and Diſtempers.</p>
            <p>AND the caſe is the ſame in the Point in hand; for the main rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why poor Sinners are no more free to change their Eſtate, to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake their firſt Husband, <hi>viz.</hi> the Devil, and the World, and to be joyned and married to Jeſus Chriſt, is becauſe they ſee not the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and miſery which they lye in and under, in the Condition in which they are.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:171083:11"/>
            <p>A SECOND Let or Hinderance in this Matter, is Perſons being ſo much in Love with their preſent States, and the Pleaſures and Profits which, as they ſuppoſe, they enjoy therein. For the proof of this, ſee that Place in <hi>Matth.</hi> 22. at the beginning: Where the Text tells us, That <hi>a great King (i. e.)</hi> God, <hi>made a Marriage for his Son, (i.e.)</hi> Chriſt; <hi>and ſent forth his Servants to call them that were bidden to the Wedding.</hi> But what ſaith the Text? Well, <hi>they would not come. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain he ſent forth other Servants to tell them that all things were ready;</hi> This was not only to invite, but alſo to perſwade: But what ſaith the Text? <hi>Ver.</hi> 5. Well, They did not only <hi>refuſe to come,</hi> but they alſo <hi>made light of it, and went their ways, one to his Farm, and another to his Merchandiſe.</hi> Alas, their Purſes were full, they had Riches enough at home; they knew not that they were <hi>wretched, poor, blind, miſerable and naked,</hi> Rev. 3.17. Yet it is not the bare having of the World, and the Things thereof, that hinders; but it is the inordinate loving thereof. This is that which ſpoils all: In 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.10. The Apoſtle tells us, That <hi>the Love of Money is the root of all Evil.</hi> Mark it; It is not the Money it ſelf; for the Creature is good; but the inordinate Love of it, this is the root of all Evil. Therefore, pray, mind what our Lord ſaith, <hi>Luke</hi> 14.26. <hi>If any man come to me, and hate not his Father and Mother, and Wife and Children, and Brethren, and Siſters; yea, and his own Life alſo, he cannot be my Diſciple.</hi> That is, Whoſoever pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeth to come to Chriſt, and hateth not all theſe things, with what elſe can be named beſides Chriſt, in compariſon of, or in competition with Chriſt, cannot be his Diſciple, and then for certain, not his Spouſe. Oh Beloved, many keep a great ſtir about Sin being the main Let in the way of Union betwixt Chriſt and a poor Soul; but, I tell you, it is not Sin, but the Love of Sin, that ſeparateth betwixt Chriſt and the Soul. See <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.15. <hi>Whoſoever loveth and maketh a Lye,</hi> is caſt out of the Holy City; not he that barely maketh a Lye, through weakneſs, or by reaſon of Temptation; but he that not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly doth ſo, but alſo loveth to do ſo; this is the Man of the Lord's An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. Therefore, ſaith <hi>David, If I delight in Sin, God will not hear my voice.</hi> This therefore is the main Let in our way of Union with Chriſt, becauſe we Love Sin, and love the World, together with the Pleaſures and Profits thereof; we love the Fleſh, and we love our Luſts, our Selves, our Works, and our own Righteouſneſs; and therefore we cannot love Chriſt. And further, provided that we ſhould hate Swearing and Drunkenneſs, and yet love Pride and Covetouſneſs, this is nothing; or if we ſhould hate Pride and Covetouſneſs, and yet love
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:171083:12"/>Deceit and Hypocryſie, we are ſtill no better: This is but as it were, to change one Devil for another, and ſo keep a Devil ſtill. But I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not enlarge.</p>
            <p>THE Third Let in our way of Union with Chriſt, which I ſhall now mention, is want of Faith in Chriſt. And truly, Beloved, this is a great Mountain in our way; indeed this is the <hi>Hydra,</hi> the Monſter-Sin, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelief;</hi> for as there is nothing impoſſible to him that believes, ſo there is nothing poſſible to him that believes not: For as Faith hath the preheminence above all other Graces, ſo Unbelief hath the preheminence of all other Vices. And how many a poor Soul is there that is both ſenſible of, troubled for, and burthened with Sin, and alſo ſees a want of, longs for, and deſires to be with Chriſt, and yet hath little or no Union with Chriſt, by reaſon of Unbelief? Yea, there are many that are weary of the World, weary of Sin, weary of the Devil, and of themſelves too, accounting in their very hearts all things nothing in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of Chriſt, and yet for all this, have little or no Fellowſhip with Chriſt, becauſe of the want of Faith. Oh, therefore this want of Faith is a great Soul-plague; it is as the Devil's Caſtle, and Tower of Defence, from whence he ſhooteth ſo many Darts at the Souls of the Afflicted. The Lord in Mercy arm us all againſt this Unbelief. And truly, my Friends, there is no reaſon for the perſons before ſpoken of, to doubt of God's fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, of all perſons in the World; for all the free and bleſſed Promiſes in the Goſpel run with a direct tendency to and upon them: I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you therefore, if there be any ſuch here this day, that you would take courage, truſt in God, and doubt no more; and the Lord give and grant you Hearts thus to do; for I know there is no ſuch pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Herb as Faith is, grows in the corrupted Garden of Mans Heart by Nature. But oh you proud, obdurate and hard-hearted ones, whoſe hearts the Lord never yet touched, nor who never yet trembled at Gods Words; to you be it ſpoken, the Dread ought to lie at your doors; for there is not a Curſe written in all Gods Book, but it runs with a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect tendency to and upon you, as little as you fear it, think of it, or are troubled for it now; yet the Day is a coming, even at the Door, when you ſhall be made to know it: The Lord God give you hearts to ſee it in due time, before it be too late, and the Offers of Grace be hid from your Fyes. But there is at this day a ſort of Profeſſors of Chriſtianity in the world, who pretend to Faith and a holy Life, or rather firſt a holy Life, and then Faith, as they ſuppoſe; and theſe are ſtill crying, Do, do, do; and upon doing, they pronounce Men bleſſed, happy and ſafe; not regarding in the mean while, whether
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:171083:12"/>ſuch have any Faith or no; or if they have, whether it be rightly founded upon Chriſt or no, without leaning to, or depending upon any thing elſe, eſpecially in point of Juſtification: But oh that ſuch Perſons would ſeriouſly conſider, 1. That Man, as Man, and whilſt cut of Chriſt, can do nothing: So ſaith Chriſt himſelf, <hi>Without me ye can do nothing, John</hi> 14.5. But the ſtrongeſt Argument that ever I met with, to convince me of the truth of this, is recorded in <hi>John</hi> 5.30. Where Chriſt ſaith thus; <hi>I can of mine own ſelf do nothing:</hi> And from hence I infer, That if the ſinleſs, ſpotleſs, and only Son of God, did acknowledge, That he could of his own ſelf do nothing, that is, as he was Man, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> then is it moſt high Preſumption for a poor mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal, ſinful, wretched Creature, Duſt and Aſhes, to ſay or think, that of himſelf, as ſeparate from the Grace, Power and Goodneſs of God in Chriſt, he can do any thing; that is, any thing acceptable or well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing to God. 2. Let them conſider, that <hi>whatſoever is not of Faith is Sin,</hi> Rom. 14.23. And alſo, that <hi>without Faith it is impoſſible to pleaſe God,</hi> Heb. 11.6. And laſtly, Let them conſider, that <hi>Faith is the Gift of God,</hi> Eph. 2.8. and a <hi>Fruit of the Spirit,</hi> Gal. 5.22. And if ſo, then, pray, what is ſinful Man in and of himſelf, but a poor, loſt, helpleſs, nothing, undone Creature: And this muſt man be made to ſee, before ever he can truly cloſe with Chriſt Jeſus in Truth and Sincerity. And when once he comes thus to be ſtript of all, and made nothing in himſelf, then is he a fit Object of Mercy, in which God once coming to work Faith in the heart, in order to an embracing of Chriſt, then a bleſſed Union betwixt Chriſt and the Soul is immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly brought forth.</p>
            <p>BUT, Fourthly and laſtly, For I cannot ſtand to mention any more Particulars; Another dreadful and moſt mighty Let in this way of Union betwixt Chriſt and his Church, is the Devil; of whom it is ſaid in another caſe, and may accordingly be ſaid in this; <hi>He that now letteth, will let, until he be taken out of the way,</hi> 2 Theſ. 2.7. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed it is him, which the young Lion in our Text doth moſt directly point at; for as the young Lion roared againſt <hi>Samſon,</hi> when he came down to <hi>Timnath,</hi> to take this Daughter of the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> to Wife, ſo the Devil roared againſt Chriſt, both when he came in the Fleſh, to purchaſe and redeem his Church; and alſo as he cometh in the Spirit, to call and ſanctifie his Church, in order to the betrothing of her unto himſelf in an everlaſting Oneneſs: But at the former of theſe, to wit, his coming in the Fleſh, the Matter in hand doth ſeem more directly to point; for in the latter, to wit, Man's Calling and Converſion, as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:171083:13"/>all a Chriſtians Life-time, after really made a Chriſtian, the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil doth not ſo directly ſtrive againſt Chriſt, as I ſaid before, as poor Chriſtians; for he deſpairs of ever doing good of him, who hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready led him captive, and appointed him his Bounds, ſaying, <hi>Hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſhalt thou go, and no further;</hi> But <hi>Oh,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>let me have a turn with Chriſtian Man; I once overcame Man when ſinleſs in Paradiſe, and perhaps I may do ſo again, though he be made ſinleſs in Chriſt,</hi> Luke 22.31, 32. But alas, poor Satan is miſtaken; for Chriſtians have now Chriſt to defend them, and to fight their Battels for them, which <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> in Paradiſe had not; and therefore, as Chriſtians, not ſo eaſily drawn to ſin, that is, to ſin with delight, as he did: And again, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided they do ſin ſtill, <hi>they have an Advocate with the Father, Jeſus Chriſt the righteous, and he is the Propitiation for their ſins:</hi> But how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, many a poor Chriſtian is many times hard put to it by the Devil; for it is not in vain that <hi>Peter</hi> exhorteth to be <hi>ſober and watchful,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>the Devil went about as a roaring Lion, ſeeking whom he might devour,</hi> 1 Pet. 5.8. For <hi>Peter</hi> knew by woful experience, how hard a thing it was to reſiſt and withſtand him. And indeed this is one main Reaſon why the righteous are ſaid to be <hi>ſcarcely ſaved,</hi> 1 Pet. 4.18. And ſee but at your leiſure what dreadful War he made againſt the Church in <hi>Revelat.</hi> 12. And what Joy the Saints made in Heaven, <hi>ver.</hi> 10. when he was caſt from thence. But why do I thus nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Scriptures? I will appeal to all your Experiences, that know any thing of God. And Beloved, let me ask you, Do you not find this Devil, this Dog of Hell, do you not find him, I ſay, tempting, toſſing and turning you over and over, to and again? Do you not find him lurking in every corner you come in; and laying Snares in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing you meddle with? Do you not find him riſing up and lying down with you, going to Bed and Board with you, in Light and Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Day and Night ſtill with you? And for ſure he deſigns you no Good; it is your dear and precious Souls he ſtill aims at: The Lord deliver us all from his hands.</p>
            <p>But perhaps you will ſay, Alas we know by moſt woful experience, that all theſe things are true, and that we are daily thus troubled with the Devil upon all Accounts; but oh, how ſhall we do to withſtand and overcome him?</p>
            <p>I Anſwer, If you would ſtand againſt, and be ſaved from the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, then flee from, and renounce your ſelves, as well as him; for if Self be kept alive in your Boſomes, the Devil will not be far from thence. Both ſinful and righteous Self muſt be put off, if once Jeſus
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:171083:13"/>Chriſt be rightly put on. And pray Sirs, further, have an eye to the Son of God, our great <hi>Samſon,</hi> who is come down in and by the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel into our Philiſtine Land, to marry us, notwithſtanding the uncir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion of our Hearts and Natures, to himſelf; who, though thou canſt put no Power, Goodneſs, Merits, nor Deſerts as a Weapon into his Hand, will yet notwithſtanding, by his own Almighty Power tear Satan in pieces like a Kid, in his own time, as <hi>Paul</hi> told the <hi>Romans,</hi> Chap. 16.20. <hi>The God of peace ſhall bruiſe Satan under your feet ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Believe in the Lord your God, ſo ſhall you be eſtabliſhed,</hi> 2 Chron. 20.20.</p>
            <p>I might now come to ſhew you ſome of the principal Ways, Means and Methods which Satan takes, and makes uſe of, in order to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbing, moleſting, and if it were poſſible, hindering of this happy Union betwixt Chriſt and Chriſtians; but Time not permitting, I muſt paſs that, and ſo come to the Fourth Thing premiſed from the general Propoſition, <hi>viz.</hi> To give you ſome Cautions, in order to a timely prevention of the Dangers occaſioned by the aforeſaid Lets; and they are theſe that follow: And firſt, To the Righteous.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>CA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>TION</hi> 1. And to ſuch, I ſay, Firſt, Have a care, That af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter God in ſome meaſure hath come in upon your hearts, and that you have had, as you ſuppoſe, ſome Taſtes of this heavenly Union, and are brought not only to ſee your ſelves to be in Death and Darkneſs by Nature; but alſo, through Mercy, to be brought into the Land of the Living, by Grace; and have ſeen the <hi>Day dawn, the Shadows flee away,</hi> and the <hi>Day-Star</hi> of Grace <hi>ariſe in your hearts,</hi> ſo as that you have been made to ſay, <hi>The Winter is paſt, the Rain is over and gone, the Flowers appear on the Earth, the time of the ſinging of Birds is come, and the voice of the Turtle is heard in my Soul,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Ariſe my Love, my Dove, my fair One, and come away:</hi> I ſay, have a care, that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all this, the Devil meet you not, and rob you of your firſt Love: God is oftentimes pleaſed to permit Satan to try his Children, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.10. <hi>The Devil ſhall caſt ſome of you into priſon, that ye may be tried.</hi> And be ſure the Devil will run at long Rope, he will ſtrain his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to the utmoſt, to do you a Miſchief; and tender Grapes are ſoon ſpoiled: And I know the Devil will often aſſault you that are in this condition, with theſe, or the like Temptations; <hi>Oh Soul,</hi> will he be ſaying, <hi>now thy Troubles are over, and thy Dangers paſt, thy Darkneſs is fled away, and Light from Heaven is broken in upon thee; thou need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:171083:14"/>therefore, to take no further care; it is not poſſible that thou ſhouldeſt err or miſcarry; thou maiſt now ſit ſtill, and take thine eaſe; for the time of thy proſperity is come; thou ſhalt ſit as a Widow, full of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row no longer; therefore take Courage, (and ſurely well thou maiſt;) for what is it that God requires in his Word, that thou haſt not done? thou haſt mourned, prayed, repented, believed, and reformed; and is not this enough? God is none ſuch a hard Maſter: Lift up thine Eyes therefore, behold the World is before thee; Is there never an Object in it well pleaſing to thee? What needeſt thou be ſo preciſe? Doſt thou not read of a Goſpel-Liberty? Thou maiſt ſafely endeavour after, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in the lawful things of this World, and yet take no harm; wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs many great and approved Profeſſors that do the ſame.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BUT Beloved, have a care of theſe and the like Temptations; for as they are of and from the Devil, ſo they tend to your Souls ruin and deſtruction: It was the great Fault of the <hi>Galatians,</hi> that they <hi>began in the Spirit, and ended in the Fleſh;</hi> and it will be no leſs fault in you: And truly Saints are not diſtreſſed and troubled for a while, that ſo afterwards they may live again to the World and to themſelves; that is but a counterfeit Converſion: But alas, we ſee too many Examples of this nature, at this day in the World; many ſet forth fair for Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, in all outward appearance, for a while, and yet afterwards wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and dry away: The Lord make all theſe Examples as ſo many awakening, warning Caveats to us, to be the more watchful; for though all ſleep till the Bridegroom's Voice be heard, yet woe to them that ſleep afterwards: Oh the many Evils occaſioned by a lukewarm Spirit! Who is able to expreſs them? But in a word, Luke warmneſs, if it prevail, ſetteth open a door, forth at which all preſent Enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God take their Flight, and in at which Satan, Sin, Death and Darkneſs come in. And truly, when once it comes to this, the Face of Heaven looks black upon ſuch a Soul: Therefore I beg of you all that hear me this day, have a care of a lukewarm Spirit.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>CA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>TION</hi> 2. Again Secondly, If you find God delivering you from this dangerous Rock of Lukewarmneſs, directing your Feet from this dreadful Path, which directly leadeth down to the Pit, ſo as that Satan can do no good of you here: Then have a care on the other hand, of ſplitting your ſelves upon the no leſs dangerous Rock of Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie and Self-conceitedneſs. And to prevent this,</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:171083:14"/>
            <p n="1">1ſt. SEE that you be found in the Faith, eſpecially in the great Article of Juſtification: 1. Holding Juſtification by Faith. 2. And that not Subjectively, but Objectively; not as a bare Act in us, but as Beholding, Receiving, Imbracing and applying of Jeſus Chriſt, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that clear and moſt precious Text, <hi>Acts</hi> 13.39. <hi>And by him all that do believe, are juſtified from all things,</hi> &amp;c. And,</p>
            <p n="2">2ly. BE careful to live Holily, and as careful to do it ſincerely; the Grace of God inforceth Holineſs, but hateth Hypocriſie: and that you may do this, 1ſt. See that you expect not that Holineſs ſhould bring you to Chriſt, but that you ſhould derive Holineſs from Chriſt, being by Faith Primarily brought unto him. 2ly. That the performance of good Duties moveth not God to give his Grace to you, but his Grace firſt given to you, and wrought in you, moveth you to perform good Duties, if you do them aright.</p>
            <p n="3">3ly. THINK not that your love to God or to Goodneſs, doth produce love to God towards you, which was not in him before; but contrariwiſe, that God's Love to you manifeſted and revealed in you, produceth and begetteth love in you, both to God, Goodneſs, and Good Men; nay, to your very Enemies. But Oh wherewith ſhall it be lamented, that this Godly Love, which always produceth Chriſtian Unity, is ſo much wanting at this day among profeſſors. But,</p>
            <p n="4">4ly. IN all your Holy Actings, do not, as it were, Act for Life, or that you may receive Life; but on the other hand Act as from Life already received from Chriſt by Faith, and revealed and wrought in your Hearts by the Spirit.</p>
            <p>LASTLY, Be not puffed up with, or by, any thing that you do, have done, or can do. Oh forget it! look over it, take Chriſt's Advice; let not the left Hand know what the right Hand doth; and when you have done whatſoever is commanded you, ſtill account your ſelves <hi>unprofitable ſervants, Luke</hi> 17.10. And be ſure you hold faſt the <hi>Foundation and Corner ſtone, Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> and bring nothing as a Ground of your Faith into the preſence, and before the Face of God, but Chriſt and him alone. Oh obſerve the words of <hi>Luther</hi> upon his Dying Bed, which are ſaid to be his laſt words! Says he, <hi>Chriſt have
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:171083:15"/>I loved, Chriſt have I feared, Chriſt have I ſerved, Chriſt hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> I preached, in Chriſt have I believed, and unto Chriſt I commende my Soul.</hi> Beloved, here was a Bleſſed end; here was a Comfortable and Glorious End: The Lord bring us all to ſuch an End for his Names ſake. And would you come to ſuch an end? then beware of Hypocriſie. But I haſte. A word or two more of Caution to the Wicked, and ſo I come to the Application.</p>
            <p>AND in the firſt place, if there be any Perſons among us this day, that are Ignorant of, and Strangers to God, and his work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings upon the Souls of his People, and that are mindleſs and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardleſs of God, Chriſt, the Goſpel, Heaven, and their Souls Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, living either in deſperate Wickedneſs, Moral Civility, or Legal Holineſs, and yet without God; Well, to all ſuch I would ſay, Oh have a care, have a care how you dally away your precious time! Conſider your Souls lie at ſtake, and if you miſs of Chriſt you are undone for ever; remember the Rich Man, <hi>Luke</hi> 16. who never lift up his Eyes till he was in Hell. Oh examine before hand, what you will do upon your Dying Beds, when you muſt take your Leave of Friends and Relations, go off the Stage of this World, and paſs into endleſs Eternity. Beloved, pray mind me, there is as it were two great Porters, if I may ſo ſpeak, which ſtand beſide the Gates of Death, <hi>viz.</hi> Chriſt and the Devil; Chriſt as it were on the right hand, and the Devil on the left, and when the Soul of a Righteous Man paſſes the Gates of Death, Chriſt, whoſe everlaſting Arms are ſtill ſpread under all his, with open Heart and Hand, is there ready to receive him, and will not ſuffer Satan as much as once to come nigh him, but will ſay, <hi>No, Satan, the time of this Souls warfare is accompliſhed; thou haſt had thy time to try and ſift him, and haſt cauſed him to feel many a bitter hour of Trouble, but I who long ſince bought him, have ſaved him from thy Hands, and will now receive him to Glory, where thou ſhalt never trouble him more; for precious to the Lord are the Death of all his Saints, and Bleſſed are the Dead which die in the Lord, from henceforth, for they reſt from their La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, Trouble and Toil.</hi> But on the other hand, when a Wicked Unbeliever dyes, and comes to paſs the Gates of Death, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently he falls into the Jaws of the Dog of Hell, <hi>i. e.</hi> the Devil, and is caught in the Arms of Satan, and ſo hurried down into Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Flames; and if he cry, <hi>Lord, ſave me; No,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>for in thy Life time thou contemnedſt my Grace and Goſpel, and caſt off my Counſel and Reproof, thou ſet light by my Death and Merits, and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:171083:15"/>would have none of my Salvation, I will therefore now Laugh at thy Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities, and mock when thy Fear cometh; Depart thou from me, O thou Worker of Iniquity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O conſider this, all you that forget God, and while it is called to day, and while the Door of the Bride-grooms Chamber ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth open, hear, fear and lay it to heart, return to the Lord, accept of Grace, and embrace thoſe things that belong to your Peace, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they be hid from your eyes: For the Devil deſigns nothing more, than to draw you on with one Temptation or another, in Blindneſs and Forgetfulneſs of God, till Death hath cloſed up your Eyes; and then he knows well enough that Hell ſhall cloſe its Mouth on your Souls: if you miſs of Chriſt, you miſs of Heaven for ever.</p>
            <p>AGAIN, <hi>Secondly,</hi> Beware that upon your turning from your evil ways, you do not cloſe with a falſe Faith in an unfound way of Religion; for it will be a ſad thing if you talk your ſelves to Hell with heavenly Words, or go to Death and Judgment with a Lie in your right-hand. But may be you will ſay, <hi>But how ſhall I turn aright?</hi> I anſwer, I ſhall direct you to the Lord's own counſel, <hi>Jer.</hi> 4.1. <hi>If thou wilt return, O Iſrael, (ſaith the Lord) return unto me.</hi> Mind the words, <hi>Return unto me:</hi> It is not enough to turn to this or that Man's particular Way or Form, nor to joyn to this or that Congregation, though never ſo pure and Apoſtolical; neither is it enough to turn from a vain and ſinful, to a good and godly Life; from Vices to Vertues, from evil and wicked Works, to an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly, holy and righteous Converſation, though all theſe are good in their places, and always certain Adjuncts of true Chriſtianity, and evermore Concomitants of true Faith in all that are truly godly, ſo far as poſſible.</p>
            <p>BUT the Root of the Matter lyes in this; a ſincere and godly turning to the Lord; I ſay, To the Lord; and a cloſing in the firſt place with Jeſus Chriſt, by Faith, as our Mediator, Advocate, and only Saviour; as our King, Prieſt, and Prophet; as our Head, Lord, King, and Husband, for ever. Taking him as of God, he is made over to us, Wiſdom, Righteouſneſs, Sanctification and Redemption; believing that he hath bought us, and paid our Debt for us; that he hath acquitted us from Sin, the Law, Curſe, Death and Hell; and that by him we are accepted of, and juſtified before God Almighty; and that our Sins are laid upon him, and his
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:171083:16"/>Righteouſneſs imputed to us by God the Father, according to that golden Text, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.21. <hi>He hath made him to be ſin for us who knew no ſin, that we might be made the righteouſneſs of God in him:</hi> And that now henceforward we muſt not live unto our ſelves, but unto him that hath redeemed us, and died for us; and that we muſt fear him, and ſerve him; not as Slaves, but as Sons; not for Rewards, but of a ready Mind, accounting it as our Meat and Drink to do the Will of God, according to his Word, knowing that a Free-will Offering is only acceptable unto God. Theſe things I commend to your Conſideration; I would enlarge further, but that time calls for a Concluſion. However take a few words of Application.</p>
            <p>AND firſt of all, by way of Examination. And becauſe we are upon a Matter of very great Importance, I deſire we may all be faithful to our own Souls herein. The ſeveral Particulars which I ſhall commend to your Conſideration, by way of Examination, are theſe following.</p>
            <p>FIRST, Pray let us examine, Whether <hi>Samſon</hi> be come down to <hi>Timnath?</hi> I mean, Whether Chriſt Jeſus be come home to our Hearts? Whether he hath given an awakening and an effectual Call, in and by the Goſpel, to our Souls, <hi>which hath brought us out of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs into his marvellous light; and out of the Kingdom and Territories of Satan, Death, and Hell, into the Kingdom of his dear Son?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>OBJECT.</hi> But may be you will ſay, <hi>But how ſhall I know it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>ANSW.</hi> To which I Anſwer, by theſe three following Marks:</p>
            <p>FIRST, If <hi>Samſon</hi> be come down to <hi>Timnath;</hi> if Chriſt be come home upon your Hearts, to call your Souls home to himſelf, as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, then hath he given you a true ſight and a ſenſe of your <hi>Phili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi> Condition, of your Uncircumciſed Eſtate, which you are in by Nature: A true ſight of which doth chiefly conſiſt in theſe five things. 1ſt. In being brought to ſee your ſelves to be the chief of Sinners, even as <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.15. 2ly. In being brought to ſee the exceeding ſinfulneſs of this Sin wherewith you are thus polluted, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.13 3ly. In being made truly ſenſible of the dreadful Curſe with the which the Law threatens you for, and becauſe of this ſin and ſinfulneſs, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.10. 4ly. In being accordingly made ſenſible of your own in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficiency,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:171083:16"/>by any worth or merit in your own ſelves, to ſatisfie for the Sin, or deliver from the Curſe, whereof you are guilty, and with the which you are attended whilſt you are in this condition. 5ly. In being brought to ſee at what an infinite diſtance you ſtand from God in this Eſtate; and conſequently to ſee how far you are, 1ſt. From Reconciliation with God; and, 2ly. Of the Certainty of your Damnation, if you be not reconciled unto God.</p>
            <p>SECONDLY, A <hi>Second</hi> Mark is this: If Chriſt hath called you to himſelf, <hi>out of darkneſs, into his moſt glorious light;</hi> then as he hath let you ſee an inſufficiency in yourſelves to ſave your ſelves, ſo he hath let you ſee an All-ſufficiency in himſelf, whereby you are brought to underſtand, that though you be wholly loſt in your ſelves, yet that there is a full and abſolute poſſibility of your being both redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and ſaved in and by Jeſus Chriſt; ſo that deſpairing in the firſt place of all power, peace and ſafety without Chriſt, you may be brought wholly and alone to confide in Chriſt for the ſame: And this is a ſure and moſt happy Condition, and I beſeech you be ſerious in the Examination of it.</p>
            <p>AND, <hi>Laſtly,</hi> The Third and laſt Mark is this: If Chriſt hath called you home to himſelf, as aforeſaid; then are your ſelves become a burthen to your ſelves, and you find your greateſt Enemies to be them of your own Houſe, which makes you call and cry day and hour unto the Lord your God to help, uphold and ſtrengthen you againſt Self, and all its Aſſiſtants; that ſo being freed from the ſame, you may be given up wholly to Chriſt Jeſus, both in Faith and Practice; which is a Condition moſt deſirable to all true Chriſtians, though God knows too many Profeſſers at this day are ſtrangers to the ſame.</p>
            <p>SECONDLY, A <hi>Second</hi> thing which I would have you to examine, is, Whether this <hi>young Lion,</hi> the great Oppoſer of Chriſt, <hi>viz.</hi> Satan, be deſtroyed and ſlain, yea or no?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>OBJECT.</hi> But may be you will ſay, <hi>How ſhall I know that?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>ANSW.</hi> If this <hi>young Lion</hi> be ſlain; I mean, If Satan be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come in and upon your account, then you may know it in ſome meaſure by theſe following things.</p>
            <p>FITST, If Satan be thus overcome, then you are made ſenſible that it was not you, but another upon your account, that did thus
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:171083:17"/>overcome him, even Chriſt Jeſus; and ſo conſequently, that not to you, but to him belongs all the Glory for evermore.</p>
            <p>SECONDLY, If Satan be thus overcome by Chriſt Jeſus, in you, and for you, then are you abundantly troubled for that you can no more love, and give Praiſe to Chriſt Jeſus for the ſame; for Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved, I am very much ſatisfied, that it is one of the greateſt Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles that a true Child of God meets withall, even becauſe he finds himſelf no more forward in loving and praiſing of Jeſus Chriſt for all his Gifts, Favours and Mercies: Yea, and truly I hope there is ſome among us this day, whoſe Minds and Spirits have been greatly burthened many a time, becauſe they could deny themſelves no more, and eſteem of Chriſt no better in Matters of this nature: And pray note it, It is a good ſign of a Chriſtian, in whomſoever theſe Thoughts do reſide; for Self-Love, Pride, and Spiritual Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, is of all things moſt contrary to God, and deſtructive to Godlineſs.</p>
            <p>BUT, <hi>Thirdly</hi> and <hi>Laſtly,</hi> If Satan be thus overcome in you, and upon your account; then are you in ſome degree united and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried to Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>OBJECT.</hi> But may be you will ſay, <hi>But how ſhall I know whether I be ſo Married to Jeſus Chriſt or no?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>ANSW.</hi> To which I anſwer: If you be Married to Jeſus Chriſt, then it will appear in theſe following things.</p>
            <p>FIRT, You will have a higher Eſteem of Jeſus Chriſt, than of any thing elſe whatſoever: Yea, he will be to you <hi>the chiefeſt among ten thouſand, even altogether lovely;</hi> ſo that you will be brought to think <hi>one day in his Courts</hi> better ſpent than a <hi>thouſand</hi> elſewhere.</p>
            <p>SECONDLY, You will think every hour a loſt hour, that is not ſpent in the fellowſhip of his Love, and enjoyment of his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence; yea, and often will you be bewailing your ſelves, that you have ſpent ſo much time without the ſame; crying out unto God after this manner, and ſaying, O Lord, how many a day and hour have I ſpent in wickedneſs and vanity, without either ſeeing or enjoying thee! O my God! which now occaſions abundance of trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to my Soul, even when I conſider it.</p>
            <p>THIRDLY, You will think your ſelves Loſers by all things you receive, in which you receive not Chriſt Jeſus. Then it will not ſatisfie you to have Lands and Livings, Gold and Silver, Wife and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:171083:17"/>Children, unleſs you have Chriſt too: Neither will it ſatisfie you to enjoy Goſpel-Priviledges, and Gracious Opportunities, unleſs you enjoy and poſſeſs Jeſus Chriſt in all and every of thoſe things; for no Wife that ſincerely loveth her Husband, doth ever account her ſelf happy in the enjoyment of any thing wherein ſhe doth not enjoy her Husband; even ſo in like manner God's dear Children are not content with any thing that they do poſſeſs or enjoy, wherein they do not poſſeſs and enjoy Jeſus Chriſt: And Oh, Sirs! let me freely ſpeak it, theſe Perſons are not content with Gifts, no, not with heavenly Gifts, without the Giver. Do they come to hear Sermons? ſtill they are ſearching for God's Power and Preſence in and under the ſame, or elſe they are not contented. Do they Pray, Read, or Receive the Sacraments? Well, ſtill it is the ſame; all things with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out God are nothing in their eſteem.</p>
            <p>FOURTHLY, If you be thus Married to Jeſus Chriſt, then are you ſoon aware of any thing that doth interpoſe betwixt Chriſt and your Souls; yea, if a Cloud do but come over the Face of the Sun of Righteouſneſs, ſo as to darken the Glorious Light thereof in your Souls, then are you quickly ſenſible of it. And if that this Cloud remain upon the Face of the Son of God, Chriſt Jeſus, ſo as that Spiritual Darkneſs do long continue in and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your Souls, O how often are you then enquiring, and ſaying, Oh why doth he hide his Face from me! and why is his Chariot-wheels ſo long in coming!</p>
            <p>FIFTHLY, If you be thus Married and United to Jeſus Chriſt our Spiritual <hi>Samſon,</hi> you are very Earneſt in the promoting of Chriſts Glory. O when you hear Perſons giving Glory to fleſhly Wiſdom, Humane Learning, Natural Abilities, Moval Civility, or any thing of the like Nature, which ſeemeth to leſſen or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogate from the Glory of Chriſt Jeſus, O how near doth this come home to your Heart; for better a great deal a true Chriſtian en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure to hear themſelves laid low, and trampled in the Duſt; yea, and accounted as bad, nay worſe than nothing, than to hear Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt abaſed and ſet below his place; O this cuts them to the very Heart!</p>
            <p>SIXTHLY, If thou be Married to Jeſus Chriſt, then it is thy Hearts deſire to walk in all his Ways, and in all things to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form to his Will and Pleaſure. A Tender and Loving Wife ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth more pleaſure in doing and obſerving her Husbands Will and Pleaſure than her own: So in like manner Chriſts Church and Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:171083:18"/>do moſt heartily deſire to do Chriſts Will; yea, and account it as their meat and drink to do the ſame.</p>
            <p>SEVENTHLY and laſtly, If thou be married to Jeſus Chriſt, then art thou oftentimes in Great Trouble that thou canſt keep no more faithful and true to him than thou doſt; yea and how of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten art thou taking occaſion, from the obſervation of thy own weakneſs and proneneſs to backſlide from God, to deteſt and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horre thy ſelf, to lay thy hand upon thy mouth, to admire Gods unſpeakable Love, and to cry out with the Church in the <hi>Lamentations,</hi> Ch. 3.22. <hi>It is of the Lords mercies that we are not conſumed, becauſe his compaſſions fail not.</hi> And hence it cometh to paſs that the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual Cry of thy Soul is, <hi>Not unto me, not unto me, but unto</hi> Samſon, even <hi>Chriſt</hi> my Lord and Husband, <hi>be all the praiſe and glory for ever and ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>MANY more things I might propoſe to your Conſideration, to be Examined by you, but time being ſpent I omit them, and ſhall only add two words more, and ſo draw to a Concluſion. And the firſt word is by way of Terror to the Wicked, who neither are Married, nor deſirous to be Married to Jeſus Chriſt. And the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond is by way of Comfort, to all ſuch as apprehending themſelves to live in the Land of the <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> afar off from God, do long, breath, groan, pray, and moſt earneſtly deſire to be brought nearer to, and wholly joyned with Jeſus Chriſt as their Lord and Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band.</p>
            <p>I begin with the firſt, <hi>viz.</hi> ſuch as neither are Married nor deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to be married to Jeſus Chriſt: And to all ſuch I ſay, that it had been better for them that they had never been born, than that they ſhould live and dye without Jeſus Chriſt; better had it been, that their bodily Eyes had never ſeen the Sun in the Firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, than that their Souls Eyes ſhould not ſee the Son of God in the Goſpel: Better had it been that ſuch had never had a being in this World, than that they ſhould have an Eternal being without Chriſt in another World: O Dear Friends, I would be plain with you, and pray mind what I ſay, <hi>As the Tree falls, ſo it lyes;</hi> no Converſion in the Grave. True, the Grave may be as a Bed to reſt in, but it will not, it cannot be as a Shop to Trade in. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let Old and Young, Rich and Poor, that hear me this day, be adviſed to turn to Jeſus Chriſt our Lord and Saviour. And Sirs, if you do but come by a true and ſincere Faith to lay hold on Jeſus Chriſt in Sincerity, fear not but it ſhall be well with
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:171083:18"/>you to Eternity. And in your turning to God, beware of this, That your outward Appearance as to Lives and Converſations, do not go before or without your Hearts and inward Inclinations: And further, have a care of ſeeking after God in another way than he himſelf hath appointed. Conſider, that not in the way of Works, but in the way of Faith we are to meet with, live and walk with Jeſus Chriſt, for <hi>the Juſt ſhall live by Faith.</hi> And pray note it, it is <hi>not every one that cryes Lord, Lord, that ſhall enter into the Kingdom of Heaven;</hi> becauſe all that profeſs the Name of Chriſt, have not Hearts endued with ſincere Love to Chriſt; and I muſt tell you, that a ſanctified Heart is better than a Silver Tongue, and a heart full of Grace is much better than a head full of Notion. Ard certain it is, that you may pretend to be Gods Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, when you are not his Sons; but undoubtedly, if you be his Sons you will be his Servants, not by conſtraint, or for Rewards, but moſt freely, and with a ready mind: And one word further I deſire to commend to you, and I deſire you to obſerve it: A Man may ſeem a Chriſtian, and not be ſo: but if a Man be a Chriſtian, he muſt of neceſſity ſeem ſo.</p>
            <p>AND ſo I come to the laſt Uſe, which is a word of Comfort to all ſuch, as apprehending themſelves to live in the Land of the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtines, I mean afar off from God, do long, breath, groan, pray, and moſt earneſtly deſire to be brought nearer to, yea, and whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be joyned with Jeſus Chriſt, as their Lord and Husband: And to all ſuch I would ſay, fear not, for your Redeemer liveth, and the moſt holy One of <hi>Iſrael</hi> will be your Refuge. He that is the God of Glory, and that inhabits Eternity, can and will help all that love him, fear him, truſt in him, and depend upon him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>OBJ.</hi> But perhaps thou wilt ſay, True, I deſire, yea and that with all my Heart, ſo far as I know it, to be made one with, and Married unto Jeſus Chriſt: But the Devil, this roaring Lyon, of whom you have ſpoken, doth ſo withſtand and oppoſe me herein, that I am afraid that what I deſire herein can never be effected: Surely never poor Soul was ſo tempted with, and oppreſſed by Satan as I am.</p>
            <p>TO which I Anſwer, Poor Soul, thou feeleſt no Mans burthen but thy own, neither doth Satans Temptations to another trouble thee, but do but thou ask another in thy Condition, and he will tell thee that he is tempted even by Satan as thou—But may be thou wilt ſay, But I think there is none in ſuch a Condition as I am. To
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:171083:19"/>which I anſwer, Why, what a State art thou in? Well, perhaps thou wilt ſay, Firſt, I am full of Sin, and ſinful pollutions, and ſo conſequently more abominable in my ſelf than a Toad: So that when I come before Chriſt Jeſus to beg Mercy and Acceptance, alas, I ſee that I deſerve none. And beſides, when I come I have almoſt always the Devil to bear me Company, on purpoſe to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent my embracing of, and being joyned unto Jeſus Chriſt, and therefore ſurely never Perſon was in my Condition: To which I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, Alas poor Soul, thou art quite miſtaken, for there is not a true Chriſtian, but is in the ſame Condition leſs or more, yea, I my ſelf could tell thee the ſame Story, and much more; yea, and that by woful Experience: But however, for thy better ſatisfaction I ſhall commend to thee an Example from the Scripture. See <hi>Zech.</hi> 3.1, 2, 3. and note it well; ſaith the Prophet there, <hi>He</hi> (ſpeaking of God) <hi>ſhewed me Joſhua the High Prieſt ſtanding before the Angel of the Lord, and Satan ſtood at his right hand to reſiſt him:</hi> And ſaith the Text, <hi>Joſhua was cloathed with filthy Garments, and ſtood before the Angel.</hi> — Now <hi>Joſhua</hi> in this place is a Figure of the Church, and the Angel of Chriſt. The Text therefore teacheth us thus much, That when the whole Church in general, or any Member in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, do come before Jeſus Chriſt, in order to Juſtification and Salvation in and by him, then and at that time they come clad with filthy Garments, ſo undeſerving of acceptance; and alſo have the Devil to bear them company, in order to the preventing of their either joyning with or confiding in Jeſus Chriſt as their Lord and Husband, accordingly as thou ſayſt of thy ſelf, ſo thou art not alone in this Condition: But pray mind how <hi>Joſhuah</hi> in this Eſtate was freed, reſcued and delivered both from his filthy Garments, and alſo from the Devil: See the third and fourth verſes. Chriſt firſt rebuked Satan, and then cauſed <hi>Joſhua</hi>'s filthy Garments to be taken away, cloathing him himſelf with changes of Raiment; and as he did to <hi>Joſhua,</hi> ſo will he do to thee, if thou believe but in him. But perhaps thou wilt ſay, Nay, but I am Poor, Barren and Unfruitful: I anſwer, Even ſo do all God's People judge themſelves to be; they are crying out of their Leanneſs daily and hourly, and think with and of themſelves, That they do nothing for God; but though they think thus of themſelves, yet God thinks otherwiſe. And indeed this I have obſerved over and over, That the Godly have ſtill ſuch low Thoughts of themſelves, and are baſe in their own Eyes; whereas the wicked, on the other hand, are proud and
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:171083:19"/>lifted up, and have high thoughts of themſelves; and it ſeems by our Saviours Words, That both the Righteous and the Wicked will have the ſame thoughts each of themſelves at the Judgment-day. See <hi>Mat.</hi> 25. from 31. to the end, where firſt he tells the Righteous, That they had fed him, cloathed and viſited him, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But they cry out, <hi>Lord, when did we ſo and ſo?</hi> Alas! they took no notice of their good doings: Well, but Chriſt did. Oh bleſſed Profeſſors! it is to be feared there is too few ſuch at this day; for moſt are looking upon what they are, have, know, and do; and Oh! this ſpoils Religion, puffs up with Pride, and undoes the Soul. But the Righteous cry out, <hi>When ſaw we thee hungry, ſick, or in Priſon, and did theſe things unto thee?</hi> But now mark when he turns him to the Wicked, ſaying, <hi>I was ſo and ſo, and yet ye did not ſuch and ſuch things unto me:</hi> They anſwer, <hi>Lord, when ſaw we thee ſo and ſo, and did not theſe things unto thee?</hi> Alas! Blind Souls, they had deluded them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with the doing of this and that all their Life time, when as they had done nothing in God's account; foraſmuch as they had not Believed on the only begotten Son of God; for not Doing but Believing brings the Soul to Jeſus, and ſo to Truth and Holineſs in and by him. Oh that Profeſſors would ſeriouſly weigh theſe things! But, alas! few do. But however, when the Lord ſhall pour forth more of his Spirit according to his Promiſe, upon his People, then ſhall they be brought to this.</p>
            <p>AND now, Dear Friends, Time and Strength being gone, I ſhall conclude, commending you to our Heavenly <hi>Samſon,</hi> even to him that is able to keep you from falling, and to preſent you faultleſs before the Face of our Fathers Glory, with exceeding Joy: To whom be aſcribed endleſs Praiſe through Infinite Ages. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>CONSIDER what you have heard, and the Lord give you Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding in all things.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:171083:20"/>
            <head>Books Sold by <hi>William Marſhall,</hi> at the Bible in <hi>Newgate-ſtreet.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>Books written by the late Reverend Dr. <hi>John Owen.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. HIs Expoſition on the whole Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> in 4 Vol. with Exercitations concerning the <hi>Meſſiah;</hi> wherein the Promiſes concerning him to be a Spiritual Redeemer of Mankind, are explained and vindicated: His Comming and Accompliſhment of his Work according to the Promiſes, is proved and confirmed. The Perſon, or who he is, declared. The whole Oeconomy of the Moſaical Law, Rites, Worſhip, and Sacrifices, is explained. And in all, the Doctrine of the Perſon, Office, and Work of the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> is opened: The Nature and Demerit of the firſt Sin is unfolded: The Opinions and Traditions of the Ancient and Modern <hi>Jews</hi> are examined: Their Objections againſt the Lord Chriſt and the Goſpel are anſwered: The Time of the Coming of the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> is ſtated; and the great fundamental Truths of the Goſpel vindicated. <hi>Folio.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. A Diſcourſe concerning the <hi>Holy Spirit:</hi> Wherein an Account is given of his Name, Nature, Perſonality, Diſpenſation, Operations and Effects. His whole Work in the Old and New Creation is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained: The Doctrine concerning vindicated from Oppoſitions and Reproaches: The Nature alſo and Neceſſity of Goſpel Holineſ; the Difference between Grace and Morality, or a Spiritual Life unto God in Evangelical Obedience, and a Courſe of Moral Vertues, are ſtated and declared. <hi>Folio.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>Books in <hi>Quarto,</hi> written by the ſame Author.
<list>
                     <item>1. THe <hi>True Nature of a Goſpel Church and its Government:</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in theſe following Particulars are diſtinctly handled. I. The ſubject Matter of the Church. II. The formal Cauſe of a particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Church. III. Of the Polity, Rule or Diſcipline of the Church in general. IV. The Officers of the Church. V. The Duty of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors of Churchs. VI. The Office of Teachers in the Church. VII. Of the Rule of the Church, or of Ruling Elders. VIII. The Nature
<pb facs="tcp:171083:20"/>of Church Polity <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>, with the Duty of Elders. IX. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>cons. X. Of Excommunication. XI. Of the Communion of Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>es. Price bound 3 <abbr>
                           <hi>s.</hi>
                        </abbr>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. The Doctrine of Juſtification by Faith, through the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>ion of the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt, explained, confirmed and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>dcated.</item>
                     <item>3. A Declaration of the Glorious Myſtery of the Perſon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> Chriſt. <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Man.</hi> With the Infinite Wiſdom, Love and Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of God in the Contrivance and Conſtitution thereof. As alſo the Grounds and Reaſons of his Incaruation, the Nature of his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry in Heaven, the Preſent State of the Church above thereon, and the Uſe of his Perſon in Religion. With an Account and Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication of the Honour, Worſhip, Faith, Love and Obedience due unto him in and from the Church.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>Books in <hi>Octavo,</hi> written by the ſame Author.
<list>
                     <item>THe Nature of Apoſtaſie from the Profeſſion of the Goſpell, and the Puniſhment of Apoſtates declared, in an Expoſition of <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.4, 5, 6. With an Enquiry into the Cauſes and Reaſons of the Decay of the Power of Religion in the World; or the preſent general Defection from the Truth, Holineſs and Worſhip of the Goſpel. Alſo, of the Proneneſs of Churches and Perſons of all ſorts unto Apoſtaſie. With Remedies and Means of <hi>Prevention.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Exercitations concerning the Name, Original, Nature, Uſe and Continuance of a Day of <hi>Sacred Reſt.</hi> Wherein the Original of the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> from the Foundation of the World, the Morality of the Fourth Commandment, with the Change of the Seventh Day are enquired into. Together with an Aſſertion of the Divine Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>Lords Day,</hi> and Practical Directions for it's due Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</item>
                     <item>The Nature, Power, Deceit, and Prevalency of the remainders of <hi>Indwelling-Sin</hi> in Believers. Together with the ways of it's work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and Means of Prevention. Opened, evinced and applyed, with a Reſolution of ſundry Caſes of Conſciences thereunto ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaining.</item>
                     <item>A Vindication of ſome Paſſages in a Diſcourſe concerning Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with God, from the Exceptions of <hi>William Sherlock,</hi> Rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor of St. <hi>George Botolph-lane.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:171083:21"/>
                     <item>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>ourſe concerning <hi>Evangelical Love, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> Peace</hi> and <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> With the Occaſions and Reaſons of preſent <hi>Differences</hi> and <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> about things Sacred and Religious. Written in the Vndi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> of the <hi>Princsples</hi> and <hi>Practice</hi> of ſome Miniſters and others.</item>
                     <item>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rief Declaration and Vindication of the Doctrine of the Tr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>. As alſo of the Perſon and Satisfaction of Chri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t. Accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>ed to the Capacity and Uſe of ſuch as may be in danger to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>educed: and the eſtabliſhment of the Truth.</item>
                     <item>A Diſcourſe of the Mortification of Sin in Believers: 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> Neceſſity, 2. The Nature, and 3. The Means of it. With a Reſolution of ſundry Caſes of Conſcience, thereunto belonging.</item>
                     <item>A Treatiſe of the Dominion of Sin and Grace; wherein Sins Reign is diſcovered, in whom it is, and in whom it is not: How the Law ſupports it; how Grace delivers from it, by ſealing up it's Dominion in the Heart: From <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.14. Bound 1 <abbr>
                           <hi>s.</hi>
                        </abbr>
                     </item>
                     <item>A brief and Impartial Account of the Nature of the <hi>Proteſtant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> it's State and Fate in the World, it's ſtrength and weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, with the Ways and Indications of the Ruine or Continuance of it's publick National Profeſſion. Price ſtitch'd 6 <abbr>
                           <hi>d.</hi>
                        </abbr>
                     </item>
                     <item>A brief Inſtruction in the Worſhip of GOD, and Diſcipline of the Churches of the New Teſtament: By way of Queſtion and Anſwer: With an Expllication and Confirmation of thoſe Anſwers. Price bound 1 <abbr>
                           <hi>s.</hi>
                        </abbr>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
